Halifax, December 6,
1917. The harbor
is on fire.
A munitionship drifts
toward the pier
burning. Thousands of
people stop to
watch. They press
their faces to
windows. They walk
down to the
waterfront. They have
no idea what's
on board. A
telegraph operator named
Vince Coleman knows.
A sailor has
just told him
he's already running
for safety alongside
his coworker, then
stops. He turns
around. There's a
passenger train coming.
300 people who
don't know what's
about to happen.
He goes back,
alone. He sends
one last message.
Hold up the
train. Ammunitionship a
fire in harbor.
Guess this will
be my last
message. Goodbye, boys.
20 seconds later,
2 ,000 tons
of TNT detonate.
The largest man
made explosion in
history until Hiroshi
Ma. A wave
of glass crosses
the city. Every
window facing the
harbor. 249 people
lose an eye
that morning. 16
lose both. Then
the water comes.
A wall of
harbor, 18 meters
high. It crosses
to the Dartmouth
shore and erases
the MIG -Maw
village at Tufts
Cove, a community
that had lived
there for generations.
1800 die, 300
live. He never
knows.